[Music]
welcome to this business Central launch
event session in the 2023 release Wave 2
watch new in
Telemetry in this session I'm going to
talk a little bit about different
insights you can get from Telemetry data
so focusing on performance and errors
talking a little bit about a new data
that is coming soon in wave in 20
version 23 or later or in a minus to 23
some tips and tricks and finally
resources for you to go home and do
more for performance since the last
launch event video for wave one we added
AI assisted performance analysis to the
powerp app so business Central is
released twice a year in these two
release waves and the minor updates to
business Central come in typically for
the online service four different miners
the
powerbi uh app and the Telemetry is
released pretty much on a monthly
schedule so what you see here in this
session is what ever was released since
May 2023 so the first is AI assisted
performance analysis each page in the
performance report now have ai
assistance um so there's a generated
summary there is key
insights uh and other things and I'll
walk you through these um to kind of
give you an idea of how you can use
this the first uh is that there is a a
text representation a summary in English
of of of whatever is happening in this
report and this is for all the reports
or the pages in the in the performance
report this might not show any data it
might not show anything interesting uh
because this really depends on what the
AI what kind of data the AI has
available if you don't have a lot of
data it might just not show you if it
has a lot of variety and variance in
that data it might show you some
insights so so don't dispair if there's
nothing here for you to
analyze the next key thing is uh is
something called key influencers a
visual that is on all these report Pages
the key influencers will analyze the
data and and and pick up patterns so for
instance for this data set the AI picked
that apparently that that there is um
one app here
where there's a regression uh there's a
performance regression and you can see
uh this app compared to other apps and
um and maybe there's something
interesting there you can then click on
whatever insights uh or Dimension to
this is interesting and then the report
will filter to that uh below and you can
kind of investigate further as a human
what the AI assisted you that this might
be interesting so key influencers is one
another uh similar analysis is top
segments again the AI will do a
segmentation of all the data and look
for patterns in in different clusters
and present you these clusters then you
can click on a segment and and that
would filter the rest of the report to
to that
segment the
third type of analysis that we added is
helping you to do root course analysis
so this is called a decomposition tree
and this is an the the AI part of this
is that the AI will actually suggest
high or low values that influence this
thing whatever that thing you are
investigating is uh in this report we're
looking at page views and for page views
we want to see what influence the the
load time of pages and then the AI would
suggest the most likely thing that
explains uh things which in this uh case
here was the table information
page if I then click the high value it
would find the next Dimension to this
problem and then finally these are not
really AI but these are just for your
convenience before you dive into the
detailed report there is now a top 10
slowest and at um both on a tabular form
and on a on a graph where you can then
kind of see what are the my top 10 most
urgent things to fix again you can click
one of these and the report will filter
to
that okay so that was
AI then a few small things we added is
that for API calls when you call into
business Central with o data and API we
have a queuing mechanism in the server
to make sure that you cannot flood the
the server with traffic and and and
degrade performance for everyone will
actually queue up these calls in
Telemetry you now have uh data about how
how much time did your API call spent in
the que and these Q time statistics are
now also showing on the incoming web
service calls uh performance
page for long running Al we added both
the total and exclusive time uh in in
this um in this data meaning that you
can you can kind of filter away uh time
spent in modal dialogues and others to
see either
what was the total time spent as seen
from the user but also what was the kind
of the tuning potential which is the
exclusive
time and for a long running Al Telemetry
we also added SQL statistics so for long
running Al you can also easily see
whether this this long runn Al is also
doing long running operations on
SQL for job cues we added the job que
entry description to Telemetry so now
the job queue performance reports have a
hierarchy here on object Name ID type
and description so it should be easy to
for you to kind of see job queue entries
um that that take a long
time and then finally for reporting uh
we also added now a section to the
powerbi report on both how long time it
takes to generate the data set as well
as how long time it took to render the
report so in case you want to dive into
performance of reports it could be that
it's either the data set or the layout
uh that where time is spent and you can
now use this visual to find that and uh
and investigate
further the second insights is errors so
in the error Telemetry and the reporting
on that we added a lot of
troubleshooting guides in docs to help
you troubleshoot uh web service errors
and these uh come with with support in
the powerp apps so first there is
improved filtering on HTTP status codes
and also visuals that that show you
errors in uh incoming web service
requests based on HTTP status so you
combine this report with a new
troubleshooting guide in docs for each
of these status Cod codes HP status
codes you can now see in docs kind of
what does a 400 code mean and how what
can I do about it so there's also
suggested Solutions directly in docs so
you can you can now go from the insights
in powerbi into docs and see okay if I
get this error what should I do go back
to your developers and ask them to go
fix
things if you do work with web services
and call in web services it's really
important that you set the user agent
when you call business Central because
if you do so these user agents will then
show up in your powerbi error report on
web services here so you can kind of see
this particular web service call failed
and it was this a this was this client
over here this whatever client could be
powerbi power automate your own client
ient if you put that uh user agent in
there you can actually see where to
troubleshoot in your
code you also get exceptions from the
server as well as Diagnostics message
from the server the AL call stack as
well so that helps you troubleshoot even
further um so which client your web
service client is getting is having a
problem and
why as a new thing in this release
actually this was backported so it's
already available in 22. X
um web service metadata wrong metadata
in the past could actually fail the full
web service stack for an environment not
anymore so from version 22. X we will
only fail the actual service calls that
where there's a metadata problem so with
this Telemetry and this report you can
now find these points that uh that are
failing um and then fix them and go to
your developers and say look this is a
problem you need to go
fix similarly similarly to uh to
incoming web services the the pages for
outgoing web services also have improved
filtering on status codes and new
visuals that also show uh status codes
um based on uh on endpoint use that
together with the troubleshooting guide
go to develop velers and ask them to fix
things in this case the developer is
likely to be the service you're calling
out to and not uh in your Al code it
could but it yeah that's probably where
the I would go we got support for aser
functions in a system module last year
and now we have also Telemetry on usage
and errors of aure functions and a
report to support that so if you call
out to aure functions from Al um there's
now also a supporting report that can
show you uh errors and you can use that
to alert and and fix
things for email module if you're using
SMTP you probably should um there's an
new there's new uh Telemetry data from
version
22.3 and this uh this new error signal
for SMTP is now reflected in the error
report on email here so so that you can
use this CT to troubleshoot email errors
and hopefully also alert on this so that
you uh that that you make sure that you
your customer's email integration
actually
works for job queue similar to to
Performance um we have descriptions um
so job Q entry descriptions is part of
telemetry we also have u a better way
for you to find non retriable job queue
exceptions because what we will do do on
the server for job cues is if the type
of exception that uh for a failed job
queue is fatal we will stop the job
queue that means you would need to kind
of go figure which job cues were stopped
and will not uh we don't want to retry
things where it's obvious that it will
fail again so you get these new uh
visuals to show you non retriable job
que exec fusions and also a way to
filter this report uh to find
those um and as I mentioned job Q
description is also part of the job que
error Telemetry and also part of the job
que error
report there's also um one thing is
stopping job cues if they fail due to
non retriable exceptions we actually
also stop job Q entries if they exceed
the number of retries and and then you
need to find out what's going on and and
then fix it and then enable again and
this new signal is also showed in the in
the job queue error report so you can
find these repeatable job queue fails
and then um and then yeah go figure
where they are go change the code and
get them enabled
again if you use the feature Telemetry
module which you should as an Al
developer uh there's an easier way to
troubleshoot feature errors um if you
use the lock lock error function in the
feature module uh we now also show you
not only the AL cold stack but we also
pass the top and bottom of this to make
sure that you can see uh what code
failed and in which parts did the
failure
occur and then finally on all job queue
sorry on all error Pages we made it
easier if there are no no if there's no
data to show we now show this green
Banner that state oh no data is
available this is great no connect
errors and so on so so if you see these
green uh banners that means that this
part of the error report is green
there's no nothing to
show all right what is coming soon um as
I mentioned we ship tet whenever it's
ready in the Sur
um so there's no need to postpone to the
next major if something can be uh put in
in in a minor update or even a platform
update in the online service so that
that means that these are Telemetry
things that is likely to come within the
next few months the first is change lock
re life cycle events
so um this whenever a table or field is
added or removed from change lock you
would get a notification or an event
here you could use this to set up alerts
in case an administrator suddenly
enables Telemetry on a ton of things um
or after the fact let's say that you
have a performance
um problem reported from Friday you can
go into this change report once it's in
in Telemetry and in the in the powerp
app and Co there's a lot of Chang log
changes to the configuration on Friday
that could be the the cause of this
performance
regression for pended extensions there
are two new classes of signal the first
is related to the the UI where an
administrator can upload um pte directly
or pendent extensions directly in the
client we now have these validations um
validation signal on that which means
that if you alert on that you can
actually see whether a customer is
trying to upload pendant extensions and
and this is failing these these
validations fail and maybe go help
them what's probably much more impactful
is that we also in the service not on
premises
validate um pended extensions on
environment against next major so we
actually try to compile them on the next
major and then this Telemetry is then
uh send whether these compilation
validations succeed or fail so that
means once you get this you can start
alerting on customers where they will be
blocked to upgrade to the next major so
I think there this alerting on that can
help a lot on getting more reactive um
proactive probably on on uh on potential
upgrade bloggers for your
customers
and then finally business events is the
the new kit on the Block for for for
version 23 and of course business events
will have coverage with Telemetry um so
there's there so you can also start
monitoring your business events usage
and errors and so on uh with
Telemetry all right a few tips and
tricks we have a new page for onboarding
signal so there's onboarding cemetry in
business Central uh and now you can also
see follow up uh on that in powerbi
could be that this is something that
helps your onboarding uh for the project
manager for controlling onboarding you
can see how environments start and
finish onboarding criteria across all
customers for the isvs in the
room um the administration report
inventory page you can now see which
major version of business Central your
app is installed on uh so you can kind
of see where your customers are on the
base app of business Central uh and then
of course see your app whether you need
to fix things in older
versions okay so if you kind of liked
all the powerbi uh reports maybe that's
something for you um this is where you
get stuff first of all the the the
powerp app on environments is available
on appsource it's called business
Central usage analytics um and the
counterpart for isvs is the app usage
analytics so both of these apps are
available on appsource um and they're
free you just need a powerbi pro license
to consume and and
refresh um specifically for powerbi the
document ation of that is under aka.ms
slbc Telemetry and under that section
there's a the full article about uh
powerbi how to enable powerbi so how to
install the apps how to configure the
apps how to use the apps so go check
that out if this is a new territory for
you a new thing we added in
documentation also under
aka.ms slbc Telemetry is
um a walkthrough example if you are new
to kql kql is the query language for
Telemetry custo query language we now
added a few a full walk through examples
uh taking you from not being able to
write kql into a small report uh we are
going taking you through analizing
report analytics so go check that out if
you want to start your journey on
analyzing kql it's not super complicated
um and we'll hold your hand through this
and after that you'll be able to kind of
slice and dice data in a different way
that what you would do with with
powerbi and I always when I talk about
alerting uh it's important that you also
check out to be proactive uh alert on
Telemetry you can do it in two different
ways one is just no code with powerbi uh
it's called powerbi metrics you can set
up a scorecard you can follow certain
metrics you can get alerted in teams no
developer is involved you can have your
own scorecard track things your
way and then if you want to be a little
bit more complicated or have other needs
uh you can you can do what we call low
code alerting with kql either use power
automate or a power app or whatever you
like Power shell I don't care um and
then
you need to have alerting conditions
what would you like to alert on these
are expressed with kql and there are
tons of samples on that available on BCT
Tech um and then you kind of just need
to have to set up whatever tool you're
using how often do you run these queries
and which channels you want to alert in
so check out our documentation on
alerting uh on docs so go do
most important thing if you haven't
enabled Cy go do it in deploy an a
application resource make sure that you
have your cost control uh done that's
part of the docs and then added to the
environment it also works on
Prem the second thing is install the
powerbi apps it requires a powerbi pro
license and this gives you insights into
usage errors performance and changes to
environments or to
apps the third go do is I think you
should start being proactive set up
alerts either with powerbi metrics with
no code or some low code with power
automate logic apps or your own solution
but the most important is number four
get data driven you start using data to
um to drive decisions in your partner
practice and this even though this
session was maybe a little bit about TR
shooting you can use Telemetry data to
get data driven on your pre-sales on
your go lives on your operations support
and ongoing sales for customers so the
full life cycle of a customer you can
cover that with datadriven decisions and
I hope you
will other relevant launch event
sessions if you are into this topic I
would uh strongly consider you
especially for
onboarding to uh to to go go to the
watch new creating customer Centric
onboarding
experiences and a counterpart for that
or maybe a a followup on that
is is uh performance testing before go
live with the performance toolkit we
actually invested a lot in these two to
make the onboarding experience better
and the performance toolkit is a way to
do concurrency testing and use it like
can the system handle this load and of
course the way to analyze all of this
performance data is telemetry and
powerbi resources um as always take your
questions or discussions to Yammer um if
it's shorter things or join the
conversation on X
Twitter um BC all is the the one and
only AKA link you need aka.ms slbc all
all the other short links are available
there if you have great ideas also for t
and other things uh the BC ideas short
URL is where you should go and of course
everything we talk about here in the
launch event is something we also
discuss in office hours where you can
also ask questions and comments so uh so
go to aka. msbc office hours to uh to
see when is the next available office
hour I do believe all the recordings for
previous office hours are there as well
and with that thank you so much for
joining this session on Telemetry I hope
you have a great business Central launch
event and watch all the other videos
thank
you